A Guide to the Charles E. Culpeper Foundation, Inc. records FA025
Rockefeller Archive Center
Charles E. Culpeper Foundation, Inc. records
1866-2001
Rockefeller Archive Center
Culpeper, Charles E.
Charles E. Culpeper Foundation
FA025
35.41 Cubic Feet
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged into 3 record groups:
Record Group 1 - Accession 1
Record Group 2 - Accession 2
Series 1065 - Photographs
Biographical/Historical note
Charles Emory Culpeper (1874-1940) was born in Rome, Georgia, to a farm family of nine children. Although he never finished high school, he was an industrious young man who worked as a store clerk in the Rome area and later as a traveling salesman. In 1899, Culpeper accepted a job selling Coca-Cola syrup to soda fountains in Philadelphia. In 1904, he was transferred to New York, where he worked as a salesman for the Coca-Cola Bottling Works of Newark and of New York. In 1917, Culpeper bought the two companies for $160,000 and combined them into the Coca-Cola Bottling Company of New York. The company prospered under his direction, and at the time of his death in 1940, his stock in it comprised the bulk of his substantial fortune.
Culpeper was highly involved in the welfare of children. Throughout his lifetime, he was instrumental in assisting boys' clubs in the New York area. In his will, Culpeper directed that a foundation be established to acquire the bulk of his fortune and conserve it for the benefit of future generations. On December 18, 1940, the Charles E. Culpeper Foundation was established.
By the late 1980s, the foundation focused its awards in medical science on three areas within the health care system: research, medical education, and clinical services. In 1990, Culpeper Foundation assets totaled approximately $118 million, and it reported disbursements of $6 million in grants that year. In 1999, the Culpeper Foundation merged with the Rockefeller Brothers Fund. A significant portion of the grants the foundation awarded were made during the period 1977-1992. The program also addressed the impact of advances in medical technology and the evolving field of managed care in a changing health care environment, as well as its effect upon individualized patient care. In 1992, support for new information technologies extended program development at secondary schools and offered technical training support for school faculty to develop foreign language curricula.
From 1993 onward, grants were issued in four broad categories: administration of justice; arts and culture; education; and health. At the college level, the foundation continued to fund computer literacy programs it had supported since the 1980s, and it extended its support to applied technologies in the humanities and social sciences as well. In 1999, the Charles E. Culpeper Foundation closed its offices in Stamford, Connecticut, and transferred its remaining operations to the Rockefeller Brothers Fund in New York City. The Brothers Fund has continued to administer remaining grant contracts and has also awarded additional grants under the terms of the merger agreement. By the end of 2007, all scheduled grants were to be satisfied; the Medical Scholars program continued until around 2010.
Scope and Contents note
The Charles E. Culpeper Foundation archives present a complete account of the foundation's activities in the years following the death of Charles E. Culpeper, during which the foundation devised and established its philanthropic mandate. The collection includes the Fiftieth Anniversary Report 1940-1990, a general overview of the foundation's involvement in the areas of health, education, arts and culture, and administration of justice, with a breakdown of funds provided for each field.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted are noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
File Plan note
Former Classification: XIII.
Arts; Philanthropy -- United States; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Charities; Medical education; Law; Medical research; Medical sciences; Medical care; Medical technology; United States; Education; Social service; Public health; Philanthropy
- Accession 1, 1866-1998; 1; 32 Cubic Feet
  Biographical/Historical note
  Biographical Sketch
  Charles Emory Culpeper, born on May 11, 1874 in Rome, Georgia, was the son of a Baptist minister and one of nine children. Mr. Culpeper's story was in the vein of a thrilling rags to riches adventure story. He was raised on a farm near Rome, and although he never finished high school, he was an industrious young man who began his career as a country store clerk and later worked as the manager of an all-night restaurant in the newspaper district of Philadelphia.
  Charles E. Culpeper joined the Coca-Cola Company in 1899 at its Philadelphia plant, selling syrup to soda fountains in the city. He was subsequently transferred to Baltimore, and in 1904, he was transferred to the New York branch, where he continued to work as a salesman. In New York City, Mr. Culpeper established Coca-Cola fountain accounts. Two assistants accompanied him so that the trio could transport sacks containing Coca-Cola trays, glasses, and other brand items. 'Charlie,' as he was known to all, was reported by friends, family, and employees alike, as having an enthusiastic and winning personality, characterized by his generosity and his ability to befriend all those he encountered. He was known for his devotion to work efforts through his wit and enthusiasm and established a close relationship with Asa S. Candler, the Atlanta druggist who purchased the rights to the unique cola formula and began a successful marketing venture to distribute Coca-Cola. Although he began his tenure as a city salesman, Culpeper later became manager of the New York office and subsequently after a switch to the bottling field, became the company's manager of New York operations in New York, Brooklyn, and Newark, New Jersey.
  In 1918, Charles E. Culpeper purchased the Coca-Cola Bottling Company of New York with his wife Daphne for approximately $160,000. Mr. Culpeper, as Chairman and President, and Mrs. Culpeper as Treasurer, chose to live in a rooftop apartment at the Bronx, New York plant during this period. Their realm of influence expanded the soft drink regional market to include suburban New York City areas and also extended to Buffalo, New York and Bridgeport, Connecticut in 1922.
  Several important milestones were reached during Mr. Culpeper's company direction. In 1929, over 100,000 gallons of syrup were bottled, and in 1930, over 31,000 cases of Coca-Cola were sold in just one day. His efforts in the industry led to the introduction of the 'six-bottle open carton' developed in 1906, which gained widespread acceptance and use. He also successfully appealed to the Atlanta headquarters of the company to obtain a franchise; as a result of these negotiations in 1929, perpetual franchise was offered to all Coca-Cola bottlers.
  Mr. Culpeper married Daphne Seybolt (February 4, 1891-September 21, 1976) in 1918, and they resided in Norwalk, Connecticut until his death on February 2, 1940. The couple had no children. At the timeof his death, the Coca-Cola Bottling Company of New York was one of the largest soft drink bottling companies worldwide. Culpeper's substantial fortune formed the basis of the Foundation possessing his name and derived from the success of this venture. Two funeral services were held: in New York City, at the Riverside Baptist Church, and at the First Baptist Church in Rome, Georgia. He is buried in the Culpeper family plot in Curryville, Georgia.
  Mr. Culpeper was highly involved in the welfare of children. Throughout his lifetime, he was instrumental in assisting boys' clubs in the New York area. In his will, he directed that a foundation be established to acquire the bulk of his fortune and to conserve it for the benefit of future generations. On December 17, 1940, the Charles E. Culpeper Foundation was established under the last Will and Testament of Mr. Culpeper. After this time, Daphne Seybolt Culpeper assisted in directing the activities of the Charles E. Culpeper Foundation as its President until 1968; she also maintained an involvement in the bottling company until her death in 1976.
  Institutional History
  The Charles E. Culpeper Foundation, Inc. (Culpeper Foundation) was incorporated in the State of New York on December 18, 1940, as a not-for-profit corporation devoted to charitable giving for both religious and educational purposes, with particular emphasis upon future generations. The three trustees appointed to direct the Foundation were Clarence R. Avery, President of the Chattanooga Glass Company, James T. Murray, successor to Mr. Culpeper as president and chairman of the Company's board, and Mrs. Daphne Seybolt Culpeper, a director and vice president of the company at that time. The will directed that the net income from the trust fund held with the Coca-Cola Bottling Company of New York to establish this charitable venture, was valued at $8 million. James T. Murray, also an attorney, was officer and director of the Foundation from this time until November 1968, at which time Frank J. McNamara, Jr. was elected Chairman of the Board. Under the joint leadership of Mrs. Culpeper and Board President Murray, the distribution of grant monies was made according to personal guidelines. Monies during this time period were extended to numerous institutions in less significant amounts.
  In 1990, Culpeper Foundation assets totaled approximately $118 million and reported disbursements of $6 million in grants that year. In 1999, the Culpeper Foundation merged with the Rockefeller Brothers Fund. A significant portion of grants awarded by the Foundation were made during the period 1977-1992. From 1993 onward, grants were issued in four broad categories: administration of justice, arts and culture, education, and health.
  The Foundation's health care program was characterized by a focus upon improving clinical skills for physicians and to aid in the pursuit of the overlap between social and ethical issues in treating patients. The program also extended to concern for the impact of advances in medical technology and the evolving field of managed care in a changing health care environment, and its effect upon individualized patient care. By the late 1980s, the Foundation focused its awards in medical science to three areas within the health care system: research, medical education, and clinical services.
  In 1992, the recognition to support new information technologies extended program development at secondary schools, offering technical training support to school faculty specifically in order to develop foreign language curricula. At the college level, the Foundation continued to support computer literacy programs since the 1980s and now recognized the need to apply technologies in the humanities and social sciences as well. Also during this time, funds were awarded to institutions supporting cultural endeavors including musical and dance performance, and cultural programs focusing on both social and natural history. Programs for disadvantaged youth and disabled citizens were also supported. These interests were represented by support of the National Theatre of the Deaf, Blind Musicians, National Theatre Workshop of the Handicapped, and the Metropolitan Museum of Art, where a program was developed to serve challenged museum patrons. Patronage also extended to the preservation of information, to include the reprinting of the out-of-print collection of 'Benjamin Franklin's Papers.'
  In 1999, the Charles E. Culpeper Foundation closed its offices in Stamford, Connecticut, and the remaining Foundation operations were transferred to the Rockefeller Brothers Fund in New York City. The Brothers Fund has continued to administer remaining grant contracts and has also awarded additional grants under the auspices of the agreement arranged. By the end of the year 2007, all grants scheduled will have been satisfied; the Medical Scholars program continues as of this writing.
  Arrangement note
  Accession 1 records are arranged in four series:
  Series 1 - Administration
  Series 2 - Grants
  Series 3 - Historical Files
  Series 4 - Francis J. McNamara, Jr. - Personal
  Immediate Source of Acquisition note
  Accession 1 of the Charles E. Culpeper Foundation, Inc. records was acquired in 1992. It was received directly from the Foundation's offices in Connecticut.
  Scope and Contents
  The archives of the Charles E. Culpeper Foundation document the institutional and personal history of the Culpeper family and contain primary sources relating to the historic evolution of American philanthropy since World War II.
  The records illustrate the close relationship between a personal philanthropic vision and the development of a corporate philanthropic institution. This collection presents a complete accounting of the Foundation's activities in the years following the death of Charles E. Culpeper, during which the Foundation devised and established its philanthropic mandate.
  The collection includes two important publications: "Fiftieth Anniversary Report 1940-1990," a general overview of the Foundation's involvement in the areas of health, education, arts and culture, and administration of justice, with a breakdown of funds provided for each field; and "Adventurous Teachers, Excellent Schools 1991," a report by Thomas James of Brown University that examines the quality of education and the caliber of faculty development programs funded by the Culpeper Foundation.
  Throughout the years the Culpeper Foundation has remained consistent with its original intentions of benefiting future generations. The Culpeper Foundation Archives document these actions and also provide great insight into the history of American philanthropy.
  - Administration, 1974-1988; 1; 2.4 Cubic Feet
    Scope and Contents note
    Series 1, Administration covers the meetings of the Investment Committee, the Grant Committee, the Board of Directors, and the annual meetings of members. The files contain correspondence, waivers, motions, financial statements, and disbursements.
    This series is arranged in 9 subseries:
    Subseries 1 - Board of Directors
    Subseries 2 - Coca-Cola Bottling Company
    Subseries 3 - Correspondence
    Subseries 4 - Grants Committee and Board Meeting
    Subseries 5 - Investment and Grant Committee Meeting
    Subseries 6 - Annual Meetings of Members
    Subseries 7 - Philip M. Drake - Grant Committee and Board Meetings
    Subseries 8 - Special Directors Meeting
    Subseries 9 - United States Trust Company Claim
    - Board of Directors, 1981-1988; 1
      - Board of Directors Meeting, Stamford, Connecticut, March 31, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Board of Directors Annual Meeting, Middletown, Connecticut, June 15, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Board of Directors Meeting, New Haven, Connecticut, October 8, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Board of Directors Meeting, Greenwich, Connecticut, December 15, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Board of Directors Meeting, Greenwich, Connecticut, March 16, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Board of Directors Annual Meeting, Greenwich, Connecticut, June 29, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Board of Directors Meeting, Stamford, Connecticut, October 20, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Board of Directors Meeting, Greenwich, Connecticut, December 15, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Board of Directors Meeting, Greenwich, Connecticut, March 1, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Board of Directors Annual Meeting, Greenwich, Connecticut, June 9, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Board of Directors Meeting, Greenwich, Connecticut, September 20, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Board of Directors Meeting, Greenwich, Connecticut, December 13, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Board of Directors Meeting, Greenwich, Connecticut, March 6, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Board of Directors Annual Meeting, Greenwich, Connecticut, June 18, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Board of Directors Meeting, Greenwich, Connecticut, September 18, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Board of Directors Meeting, Greenwich, Connecticut, December 13, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Board of Directors Meeting, Greenwich, Connecticut, March 26, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Board of Directors Annual Meeting, Middletown, Connecticut, June 26, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Board of Directors Meeting, Greenwich, Connecticut, October 16, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Board of Directors Meeting, Greenwich, Connecticut, December 18, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Board of Directors Meeting, Greenwich, Connecticut, March 3, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Board of Directors Annual Meeting, Middletown, Connecticut, June 19, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Board of Directors Meeting, Greenwich, Connecticut, September 30, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Board of Directors Meeting, Greenwich, Connecticut, December 16, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Board of Directors Meeting, Greenwich, Connecticut, March 5, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Board of Directors Annual Meeting, Greenwich, Connecticut, June 23, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Board of Directors Meeting, Greenwich, Connecticut, September 16, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Board of Directors Meeting, Greenwich, Connecticut, December 15, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Board of Directors Meeting, New York, New York, March 30, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - Board of Directors Annual Meeting, Middletown, Connecticut, June 22, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - Board of Directors Meeting, New York, New York, October 11, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Coca-Cola Bottling Company, 1979-1980; 2
      - Coca-Cola Bottling Company, March 1979-May 1980 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence, 1974-1988; 3
      - Correspondence, October 1974-March 1987 (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - Correspondence, December 1978-December 1979 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - Correspondence, November 1979-December 1980 (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - Correspondence, March 1980-December 1983 (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - Correspondence, October 1980-October 1981 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - Correspondence, January 1982-January 1984 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - Correspondence, January 1983-December 1984 (Box 4, Folder 39)
      - Correspondence, January-November 1985 (Box 4, Folder 40)
      - Correspondence, November 1985-August 1987 (Box 4, Folder 41)
      - Correspondence, January 1987-June 1988 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Grants Committee and Board Meeting, 1984; 4
      - Grants Committee and Board Meeting, September 18, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 43)
      - Grants Committee and Board Meeting, December 13, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Investment and Grant Committee Meeting, 1988; 5
      - Investment and Grant Committee Meeting, New York, New York, November 16, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Annual Meetings of Members, 1981-1987; 6
      - Annual Meeting of Members, Greenwich, Connecticut, June 15, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 46)
      - Annual Meeting of Members, New York, New York, May 4, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 47)
      - Annual Meeting of Members, New York, New York, May 22, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 48)
      - Annual Meeting of Members, Stamford, Connecticut, May 23, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 49)
      - Annual Meeting of Members, New York, New York, June 10, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 50)
      - Annual Meeting of Members, Stamford, Connecticut, May 18, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Philip M. Drake - Grant Committee and Board Meetings, 1985-1988; 7
      - Grant Committee, March 26, 1985; Board Meeting, March 26, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 52)
      - Grant Committee, June 13, 1985; Board Meeting, June 26, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 53)
      - Grant Committee, September 25, 1985; Board Meeting, October 16, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 54)
      - Grant Committee, December 18, 1985; Board Meeting, December 18, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 55)
      - Grant Committee, April 3, 1986; Board Meeting, April 3, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 56)
      - Grant Committee, June 13, 1986; Board Meeting, June 19, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 57)
      - Grant Committee, September 16, 1986; Board Meeting, September 30, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 58)
      - Grant Committee, December 8, 1986; Board Meeting, December 16, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 59)
      - Grant Committee, February 12, 1987; Board Meeting, March 5, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 60)
      - Grant Committee, June 23, 1987; Board Meeting, June 23, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 61)
      - Grant Committee, September 16, 1987; Board Meeting, September 16, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 62)
      - Grant Committee, December 15, 1987; Board Meeting, December 15, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 63)
      - Grant Committee, March 30, 1988; Board Meeting, March 30, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 64)
      - Grant Committee, May 17, 1988; Board Meeting, June 22, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 65)
      - Grant Committee, August 23, 1988; Board Meeting, October 11, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 66)
      - Grant Committee, November 30, 1988; Board Meeting, December 14, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 67)
    - Special Directors Meeting, 1981; 8
      - Special Directors Meeting, New York City, New York, July 15, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 68)
    - United States Trust Company Claim, 1980-1981; 9
      - United States Trust Company Claim, September 1980-January 1981 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Grants, 1969-1990; 2; 5.2 Cubic Feet
    Series 2, Grants contains lists of grants, financial statements, grant applications, and general correspondence documenting the administration of grants.
    This series is arranged in 5 subseries:
    Subseries 1 - Grants
    Subseries 2 - Medical Research Program
    Subseries 3 - Medical Sciences Fellowships
    Subseries 4 - Social Sciences Fellowships
    Subseries 5 - Visiting Professorships
    - Grants, 1969-1987; 1
      - ACT-American (R), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
        A. C. T. for Families, Children and Youth, 1983; Albertus Magnus College, 1978; Alliance To Save Energy, 1981; American Association of Blood Banks, 1981; American College of Surgeons, 1980; American Council of Learned Societies, 1983; American Craft Council, 1982; American Red Cross, Farmington, Connecticut, 1982.
      - American (S)-Bo, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
        American Shakespeare, 1979; American Youth Symphony and Chorus, 1973; Association for the Help of Retarded Children, 1969; Barnwell County Museum, 1978; Baylor College of Medicine, 1977; The Beaumont Homestead, 1978; Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation, 1982; Berea College, 1976; Bethesda Hospital Association, Inc., 1971; Billy Graham New York Crusade, 1969; Bloomfield Public Library, 1980; Bob Jones University, 1969; Board of Education of the City of New York, 1982; Boston College, 1969; Boys Scouts of America, Greater New York Council, 1969; Boys Athletic League, 1970; Boys Brotherhood Republic, 1970; The Boys Club of Newark, 1971; Boys Town of Italy, Inc.
      - Brid-Carm, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Bridgeville Public Library, 1979 Brigham Young University, 1972 Brooklyn Academy of Music, 1987 Brooklyn Philharmonic Symphony Orchestra, 1980 Capuchin Franciscan Friars, 1978 Carmelite Sisters for the Aged, 1969
      - Carnegie Institution of Washington, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Carr-Colu, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)